<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Anniversary ode, upon the Kings birth day. May 29. Written for this yeare 1654. Being his 24 yeare. To his Majesty.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75374</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3241</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E745_24</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207079</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866151</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866151</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118415</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75374)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118415)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 114:E745[24])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Anniversary ode, upon the Kings birth day. May 29. Written for this yeare 1654. Being his 24 yeare. To his Majesty.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Samuel Brown,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Hague :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118415:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANNIVERSARY ODE, UPON The Kings Birth day. <hi>May</hi> 29. <hi>Written for this Yeare</hi> 1654. <hi>being his</hi> 24 <hi>Yeare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>HAGUE,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Browne,</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="ode">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118415:2"/>
            <head>An Anniverſarie Ode, <hi>Upon the Kings Birth-day,</hi> May <hi>29.</hi> Written for this Yeere <hi>1654.</hi> being his <hi>24.</hi> Yeere.</head>
            <head type="sub">To his Majeſty.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>(I)</head>
               <l>THe day ennobled by your royall Birth</l>
               <l>Is now againe returnd,</l>
               <l>But not ſo bright as when to her our fumes firſt burn'd,</l>
               <l>A ſmile ſo pleaſant dimples not the Earth,</l>
               <l>Nor caſt the flowers ſuch fragor forth:</l>
               <l>Nor ſhines the Sun ſo cleare, but hides his Rayes as if he mournd.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118415:3"/>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>(II)</head>
               <l>The winged <hi>Chorus</hi> warbles not a Song</l>
               <l>With ſweetneſs crownd and Art,</l>
               <l>But lame and wrinkled, ſuch as wants the chiefeſt part.</l>
               <l>Sweet <hi>Philomela's</hi> throat is yet unſtrung:</l>
               <l>Nor doe the Nimphes yet dance along</l>
               <l>The Plains, but ſigh, alas they want the maſter of their ſport.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>(III)</head>
               <l>And that is you, Great Sir, their joynts are numb</l>
               <l>Leſſe them your eyes inflame.</l>
               <l>The Birds delight to ſing no accent but your Name,</l>
               <l>And daring not, are either hoarſe or dumb.</l>
               <l>The Sun wants light too til you come,</l>
               <l>For it is you muſt make our day, &amp; not his ſickly beam.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118415:3"/>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>(IV)</head>
               <l>Ariſe Great Planet then in your own Sphear,</l>
               <l>And our Devotions daign</l>
               <l>To celebrat your riſe. Their powrs each quire ſhal ſtrain</l>
               <l>For acclamations to ſalute your eare.</l>
               <l>The Sun ſhall put on lookes moſt clear</l>
               <l>Not with you to vie luſtre, but ſhew how much yours his ſtain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>(V)</head>
               <l>Nymphs to your name ſhall meaſure many a round,</l>
               <l>Upon the flowry green;</l>
               <l>And earth, by influence of your eyes, be gay agen,</l>
               <l>And every where with fragrant Roſes crownd,</l>
               <l>Which now droop on their ſtalkes froſt bound,</l>
               <l>And being your flowers, care by no eyes but yours to bee ſeene.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118415:4"/>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>(VI)</head>
               <l>Soon, with good Omens, dawne that happy day</l>
               <l>Wherin your royall ſeat</l>
               <l>Glad we ſhall with your ſacred luſtre ſee repleat.</l>
               <l>Then to the Pomp each eye glad teares ſhall pay,</l>
               <l>Prayers each pious heart, and ſay</l>
               <l>Long may dread <hi>CHARLES,</hi> your Preſence make your Brittaine truly great.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>(VII)</head>
               <l>Till that day comes to th' joy of Earth and Heaven,</l>
               <l>(For come it ſurely will,</l>
               <l>If Juſtice has her ſword, and equall Ballance ſtill;</l>
               <l>Or if to Muſes to ſee ought tis given)</l>
               <l>Think theſe dire foggs which ſhall be driven</l>
               <l>Fore you, but ſent to try how the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your virtue can diſpel.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118415:4"/>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>(VIII)</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffliction is the beſt of Schooles, and gives</l>
               <l>Luſtre to happineſſe.</l>
               <l>You are a mine of Gold, thinke each year of diſtreſſe</l>
               <l>Another heat, by which <hi>Jove</hi> onely drives</l>
               <l>You to refine, till he atchives</l>
               <l>Your worth fit for the height he meanes you, then his little leſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>(IX)</head>
               <l>As doth the Sun by an Eclipſe indear</l>
               <l>Himſelfe in our eſteem:</l>
               <l>So ſhall you brighter riſe with a triumphant beame</l>
               <l>After ſo many and ſo darke a yeare.</l>
               <l>And long ſhine in your Native Sphear,</l>
               <l>Whilſt fartheſt ſeas ſhal hardly bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d your powr, or ſtars your fame</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118415:5"/>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>(X)</head>
               <l>Good by its want is knowne: then dearly may</l>
               <l>Your People after warres</l>
               <l>Prize you &amp; peace like Jems long loſt, &amp; double cares</l>
               <l>With duty their late error to repay.</l>
               <l>Be their joy many a geniall day,</l>
               <l>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> late, with Palms &amp; Lawrels crownd, afce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the Throne of ſtars.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118415:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
